Guide to the Eli Smith Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Eli Smith Family Papers
1821-1964
RG 124
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(9 boxes)
Letters, journals, and writings in this record group document Eli Smith's missionary work in the Middle East. Letters of his third wife, Mehitable Simpkins Butler Smith, provide valuable documentation of her ten years in the Middle East. Research materials gathered by Margaret Leavy complement the original holdings. Eli Smith, an early missionary to the Middle East serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, is best known for his translation of the Bible into Arabic.
Smith, Eli, 1801-1857
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the descendants of Eli Smith, including Margaret Russell Leavy.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1801 Born in Northford, CT
1821 Graduated from Yale College
1826 Ordained into the ministry Graduated from Andover Theological Seminary Appointed by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions as associate editor of its publishing house in Malta
1829, 1830 Travels through Greece, Asia Minor, Armenia, Georgia into Persia led to publication of a book entitled Researches of the Rev. E. Smith and Rev. H.G.O. Dwight in Armenia: Including a Journey through Asia Minor and into Georgia and Persia, with a Visit to the Nestorian and Chaldean Christianity of Oormiah and Salmas.
1833 Married Sarah Lanman Huntington (died 1836)
1838 Traveled with Edward Robinson through Sinai, Palestine and southern Syria
1841 Married Maria Ward Chapin (died 1842); one son born, Charles H. Smith, who later became Larned Professor of History of Yale University
1846 Married Mehitable Simpkins Butler; children: two daughters and three sons
1844-1857 Smith worked on the translation of the Bible into Arabic under the auspices of the American Bible Society and the American Mission in Syria
1857 Died in Beirut
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia
IV. Photographs and Drawings
V. Research Materials of Margaret Russell Leavy
Eli Smith was a prominent early missionary to the Middle East. The letters, journals, and writings in this collection document his important role in the designing of Arabic fonts and translation of the Scriptures into Arabic, his explorations of the Middle East, and his life and work in general. This collection is also valuable for its documentation of the life of Mehitable Butler Smith, Eli's third wife, who spent ten years in the Middle East. Her letters to her family in America provide regular, detailed descriptions of her daily life as missionary wife and mother during this early era.
Series V, Research Materials of Margaret Russell Leavy, contains notes and photocopies gathered by Mrs. Leavy in the process of her research on Eli Smith and his family. Included are some material copied or transcribed from the notable collection of Eli Smith Papers held at Harvard's Houghton Library. The repositories from which the photocopies and transcripts were obtained are noted on the materials donated by Mrs. Leavy. Some transcripts prepared by Mrs. Leavy of original letters held in the Yale Divinity Library have been interfiled with the originals in Series I. Series V concludes with drafts of the major work on Smith that Margaret Leavy was preparing. Two works by Margaret Leavy related to Eli Smith are in the Library's cataloged collection: Eli Smith and the Arabic Bible, Yale Divinity School Library Occasional Publication No. 4, (1993), and "Looking for the Armenians: Eli Smith's Missionary Adventures 1830-1831" published in Transactions of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, Vol. 50 (Dec., 1992).
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia
IV. Photographs and Drawings
V. Research Materials of Margaret Russell Leavy
Bible -- Translating; Missions -- Syria; Smith, Eli, 1801-1857; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
- Correspondence, Series I
  - ES to brother, Benjamin Smith
    - from Yale College, Union Academy (Georgia), Andover Seminary, 1821-1825 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - from Malta, Beirut, Erzurum, 1826-1830 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - from Northford (Connecticut), Boston, Mt. Lebanon, Beirut, Smyrna, 1833-1837 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - from Charlestown (Massachusetts), Beirut, 1840-1844 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - from Beirut, Mt. Lebanon, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ES from brother, Benjamin Smith
    - from Northford, CT, 1827 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - ES to other family members
    - to parents, parents-in-law, from Bennington, Beirut, Mt. Lebanon, 1833, 1842-1849 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - to L.I. Hoadly (brother-in-law), from Rochester, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - to William Thompson (brother-in-law), from Mt. Lebanon, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - to Mrs. William Thompson (sister-in-law), from Beirut, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - to Mehitable (Hetty) Butler (prior to marriage), 1846 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - to Mehitable (Hetty) Butler Smith (wife), incl. from Cyprus, Constantinople, Trezibond, 1848 (?), 1856, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10, 11)
    - to/from children (Charles, Mary, Sarah), 1856, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ES to others
    - incl. to Henry White (excerpt) and to Rev. Ward in India (transcription), 1831-1856 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Dying Message of Rev. E. Smith to Dr. DeForest", 1857 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ES from others
    - Jonah Brewer, from Constantinople, Smyrna, Malta, 1827-1828 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Gio. Caravella, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - R. K. Finch, from Gibralter, 1827 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - William C. Fowler, from Middlebury, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - D.L. Goodwin, from Wilkinsonville, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Homan Hallock, from Malta, 1827 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Harris & Co., from Alexandria, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Assaad Jacob (Asaad El Khaiat), from Beirut, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - D. Macpherson, from Alexandria, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - J. Maltby, from Sutton, MA and "Missionary Rooms", 1827, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - T. Muller, from Cairo, Alexandria, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Mehitable (Hetty) Butler Smith to family members in the U.S.
    - from Green Bay, Wisconsin, Northampton (?) (prior to marriage), (1846?) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - incl. account of voyage to Beirut, 1846 Nov-1847 Feb (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - from Beirut, Bhamdoun (Mt. Lebanon), 1847 Mar-Sep (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - from Beirut, Bhamdoun, Abieh, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - from Beirut, Bhamdoun, Jaffa, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - from Beirut, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - from Beirut, Bhamdoun, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - from Beirut, Bhamdoun, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - from Beirut, 1854-1856 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - from Beirut re. death of husband, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - from Beirut, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - MBS to/from others
    - to ES, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - from Charles, 1857, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - to Charles, 1862-1865, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - incl. from Azariah Smith, William Benton, Edward Robinson, President T.D. Woolsey of Yale, 1848-1865, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Charles H. Smith
    - incl. to/from cousin, uncles, sister, 1852-1867 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - incl. from James Ford Rhodes, T.T. Munger, 1890-1930, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Other correspondence
    - C.C. Aratoon to Jacob Wortabet (?) (translation from Armenian), 1831 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - to "Brethren of the Syrian Mission" from Rufus Anderson, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - to Dr. Stearns from Henry Harris Jessup, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - to Dr. Thompson from classmate of ES re. conversion of ES in 1820, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - to Benjamin Smith from James S. Dennis, Librarian of the Syria Mission, incl. info. re. translation work of Eli Smith, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - W.R. Dwight to Miss Butler, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Writings, Series II
  - Writings of Eli Smith
    - Journals: #1, 2, 3, c. 1829-1830 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Journals: #4, 5, 6, c. 1829-1830 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Journals, 1848, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Notebooks: one of quotations; one recording correspondence of ES, c. 1830, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - printed address: "Trials of Missionaries", 1832 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - printed address: "The Missionary Character", 1840 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Reports on the translation of the Scriptures into Arabic, 1844, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Translation by ES of "A Treatise on Arabic Music", chiefly from a work by Mikhail Meshakah of Damascus (offprint from Journal of American Oriental Society and holograph ms.) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Researches of the Rev. E. Smith and Rev. H.G.O. Dwight in Armenia by Eli Smith: 2 volumes, with annotations and enclosures, 1833 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Writings of Mehitable Butler Smith
    - Journal - brief accounts of journeys, 1846-1850 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Two accounts of her years in Syria, after 1857 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Ms. article submitted to The Congregationalist re. early women's mission work; "Ancient History of Armenia", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "In Memoriam of my Husband"; "Protestant Movement in Hasbelga, Arizona" (Box 2, Folder 15a)
  - Writings of Charles H. Smith
    - Journal of trip to Constantinople, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Concerning Eli Smith - A Brief History of His Life and Work" (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Writings of others
    - Unidentified ms. article submitted to the "Scientific Journal", 1825 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper account of address by ES at meeting of Foreign Missionary Society in New York ( Morning Herald, New York), 1840 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Monody on the Death of Dr. Eli Smith" by Naseef el Gazjy, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Publication Work of the American Press, Beirut" by F.E. Hoskins, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Data Furnished by Dr. C.V.A. Van Dyck with Reference to the Translation of the Scriptures into the Arabic Language under the Auspices of the American Mission in Syria and the American Bible Society", 1885 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Brief Documentary History of the Translation of the Scriptures into the Arabic Language by Rev. Eli Smith, D.D. and Rev. C.V.A. Van Dyck, D.D.", 1900 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series III
  - Notes, excerpts collected by family members re. life and work of Eli Smith/List of writings by ES (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Eli Smith's last words to his son, Charles, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lock of hair, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bill for board at Seminary, 1825 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous memorabilia relating to Hetty Smith, 1840s-1893 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous memorabilia relating to Charles H. Smith, 1866-1909 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 2 volume family Bible, including genealogical material re. Smith family (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Arabic Bible inscribed "To the honored memory of Eli Smith from his unworthy successor in the work, C.V.A. Van Dyck", 1867 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Arabic language material: "The Sweet Story of Jesus" by Mrs. J.D. Date inscribed by S.M. Zwemer, (1912) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Arabic language material (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Robe and hat worn by Eli Smith while on horseback trips to Syria (Box 8)
- Photographs/Drawings, n.d.; Series IV
  - Portraits of Eli Smith, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Portraits of Sarah Huntington Smith and Maria Chain Smith (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Illustration of the Theological Institute at East Windsor (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, incl. The Protestant Female Seminary at Beirut, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Research Materials of Margaret Russell Leavy, Series V
  - Family correspondence
    - Eli to sister Hannah, 1827 Jun 23 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Eli to Sarah Huntington Smith's father, 1842 Jun, Nov (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Sarah to Lydia Sigourne and Rufus Anderson, 1830 Dec - 1831 Sep (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Mehitable (Hetty) to sons Ned and Ben, 1883 Jun (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Eli Smith to others
    - To Rufus Anderson re. ordination, 1826 Apr (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - To Rufus Anderson from Malta and Beirut, 1827 Mar, Jun, 1828 Aug (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - To Rufus Anderson, 1828 Sep, 1829 Dec (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - To Rufus Anderson, 1830 Jan, 1831 Mar (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - To Rufus Anderson, 1831 Sep (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - To Isaac Bird from Beirut, 1826 Dec, 1827 Sep, Nov (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - To Isaac Bird, 1850 Mar, Nov, 1851 Jun (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - To Chasseaud, 1842 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - To Jeremiah Evarts, 1827 Jan, Mar, 1828 Mar, Jun (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - To Jeremiah Evarts, 1828 Oct, Dec, 1829 Jan (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - To Jeremiah Evarts, 1830 May (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - ES and H.G.O. Dwight to Evarts, 1830 Jun (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - ES and H.G.O. Dwight to Evarts, 1831 Jan (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - ES and H.G.O. Dwight to Evarts, 1831 Jan, Mar, Nov (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - To Goodell, 1831 Jan (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - To Hoadley, 1831 Feb (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - To Jowett (from Bird, Goodell, and ES), 1829 Feb (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - To Edw. Robinson, 1852 Sep (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - To Moses Stuart, 1832 Jan (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - To Henry White, 1831 Oct (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - To Leonard Wood, 1826 May (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - To Society of Inquiry, Andover Seminary, 1829, 1840 (Box 6, Folder 25a)
  - Correspondence of others
    - Smylie Robinson to ES, 1852 Jul, 1856 May (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - J.L. Porter, Henry Hill, and James Gordon to ES, 1852, 1856 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Henry Jessup to Dr. Stearus, 1856 Aug (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Extract from Jessup letter, 1856 Aug (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - John Nicolayson to Bird, Goodell, and ES, 1827 Dec (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - H.G.O. Dwight from Tebreez, 1830 Dec (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - G.B. Whiting to Isaac Bird, 1841 Nov (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Writings of Eli Smith
    - Dissertation, Andover Seminary (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - "Use of the Press in the East", 1829-1830 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - "Syria: Hints re. Political State", 1829 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Collected material / notes / fragments
    - Fragmentary writings of ES, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Memoir of Rev. Henry Martyn, 1844 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Published material re. ES, 1833 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Excerpts from letters of various people, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Letter in French by ES in an autograph book, 1821 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Letter fragments, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Letter to ES granddaugher and excerpt from "A Land of Blessing" by John Brinton, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Writings by Margaret Leavy Russell
    - Drafts of Chapters 1 -11, Biography of Eli Smith (Box 7, Folder 42)